<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A briefe treatise against detractors of dignities. Published by Ra: Rugbie Esquire. Allowed by authoritie</title>
            <author>Rugbie, Ralph.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1622</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 35 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 15 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A11178</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 21444</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S106128</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99841853</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99841853</idno>
            <idno type="VID">6468</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A11178)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 6468)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 581:14)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A briefe treatise against detractors of dignities. Published by Ra: Rugbie Esquire. Allowed by authoritie</title>
                  <author>Rugbie, Ralph.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 26 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by George Eld,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1622.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Folger Shakespeare Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Nobility --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-03</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-03</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-05</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-05</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:6468:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:6468:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>
               <hi>A BRIEFE</hi> TREATISE AGAINST DETRACTORS OF <hi>DIGNITIES.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Publiſhed</hi> BY RA: RVGBIE Eſquire.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Allowed by Authoritie.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed by <hi>George Eld.</hi> 1622.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:6468:2"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:6468:2"/>
            <head>AGAINST DETRACTORS OF DIGNITIES.</head>
            <p>
               <hi>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">N</seg>Imium admiror ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtram hanc inſolen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiam,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Tho: Walſingham pag. <hi>21</hi> n. <hi>30.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>eo quòd ſapi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>entium miniſterium, &amp; gradus vſurpa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtis, ſapientiae autem ſtudium, &amp; ope<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ram neglexiſtis;</hi> It was a ſaying of King <hi>Aelfrea's</hi> vnto certaine per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons, which did take vpon them to iudge without learning, and may be well applied to thoſe, who que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtion <hi>Dignities,</hi> and preſume to cenſure <hi>Statum &amp; Dignitatem Baro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nettorum,</hi> thus without any true Precedent, or ground. It is ſhewed
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:6468:3"/>
in the booke publiſhed by his Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ieſtie touching the Creation of <hi>Baronets:</hi>
               <note place="margin">The Booke publiſhed by his Maieſtie, touching the creation of <hi>Baronets, pag.</hi> 19. <hi>printed</hi> 1611.</note> 
               <hi>That there is nothing of honor, or value, which is ſought, or deſired (be the motives never ſo good) but may receive ſcandall from ſome, who wanting the ſame good affection to the publique, or being in other conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derations incapable, can be contented out of enuy to thoſe, that are ſo pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferred, to caſt aſperſions and imputa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions vpon them:</hi> And out of which of theſe, or whether from them all this proceeds I know not: but cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine I am, great was their error, to reach at prerogatives ſo tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcendent, and of this high myſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie: when as no <hi>Democraticall</hi> go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uernment could ever aſcend vnto it, it being an Imperiall right, due onely to <hi>Monarchs</hi> to diſpoſe of <hi>Dignities.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Regnerus Sixtinus de Iure rega: ca. <hi>2.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Eſtius Regalium, vel ius Imperij, creandi Magiſtratus, dandi Inſignia Nobilitatis, ſive Nobiles cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>andi,
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:6468:3"/>
ad famam &amp; honores reſtituen di: Regnerus Sixtinus de Iure Rega:</hi> And herewith agrees the Act of 31. of King H: 8.<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Stat:</hi> 31. <hi>H:</hi> 8. <hi>cap:</hi> 10.</note> 
               <hi>That it appertai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth to the Kings Prerogative Royall to give ſuch honor, reputation,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>See alſo</hi> Smiths Common wealth of England, pag: <hi>28.</hi> &amp; <hi>48.</hi> accord</note> 
               <hi>and place as to his moſt excellent wiſdome ſhall ſeeme meet.</hi> Wherein his Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ieſtie hath that abſolute power, that if it had pleaſed his <hi>Highnes,</hi> there might haue beene as well in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerted the like Clauſe in their Let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters Patents, for the Creation of this <hi>Dignity,</hi> as was formerly in a Charter made by his Royall <hi>Aun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſter</hi> King <hi>H:</hi> 7. ſc<hi rend="sup">t</hi>.<note place="margin">
                  <hi>2.</hi> Parte Patent: anno <hi>1.</hi> H: <hi>7.</hi> memb. <hi>21.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Quod Rex non vult arguendum, communicandum, aut diſputandum, per quoſcun<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan>.</hi> The which followeth the opinion of <hi>Bracton, Iuſtice,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Bracton f: <hi>6.</hi> &amp; f: <hi>34.</hi>
               </note> in the time of King <hi>H.</hi> 3. ſc<hi rend="sup">t</hi>. <hi>De Chartis Regijs, &amp; factis Regum, non debent, nec poſſunt priva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tae perſonae diſputare.</hi> And that it is againſt the duty of a ſubiect, to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teriorate
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:6468:4"/>
his <hi>Highnes Prerogative.</hi> See the <hi>Mirror of Iuſtice,</hi>
               <note place="margin">The Mirror of Iuſtice, cap. <hi>5.</hi>
               </note> that by the auncient Common Law of En<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>gland, It was held <hi>a crime againſt Maieſtie: And that he was periur'd againſt the oath of a Subiect,</hi>
               <note place="margin">See the Stat: 36. <hi>E:</hi> 3. <hi>cap:</hi> 16. The care had for preſeruation of the rights of the Crowne.</note> 
               <hi>who did any way ſubſtract, or diminiſh the Rights, or Prerogatives of the King:</hi> Yet that theſe nevertheleſſe will impugne his Maieſties <hi>Preroga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive,</hi> and diſable his <hi>Highnes</hi> in that power his Royall Progenitors had: This ſhewes they did not as the wiſe men of the Eaſt, (in <hi>Math.</hi> 2.<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Math:</hi> 2. Dier f: <hi>94.</hi> Selden Hon: pag: <hi>208.</hi> Co: li: <hi>7.</hi> f. <hi>33.</hi> Ranulphus <hi>of</hi> Cheſter f: <hi>387.</hi> Camden Brit: pag: <hi>165.</hi> &amp; <hi>167.</hi>
               </note>) follow the right ſtarre. Did not King <hi>E:</hi> 3. create <hi>Dukes,</hi> and King <hi>R:</hi> 2. <hi>Marqueſſes</hi> to be he<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reditary <hi>Dignities,</hi> to precede, and goe before <hi>Earles,</hi> and <hi>Barons,</hi> that were farre auncienter? Did not af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terwards King <hi>H:</hi>
               <note place="margin">Davis Report: f: <hi>60.</hi> Co: li: <hi>9.</hi> f: <hi>124.</hi>
               </note> 6. create <hi>Viſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count's</hi> to be an hereditary <hi>Dignity</hi> likewiſe, and gave them the place and precedency of <hi>Barons?</hi> Was
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:6468:4"/>
not alſo the Inſtitution of the Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der of the Garter,<note place="margin">Smiths Common-wealth, pag. <hi>25.</hi> Camden Brit. pag. <hi>171. 172.</hi> Selden Hon. pag. <hi>353. 359. 362.</hi>
               </note> and <hi>Banneret's</hi> created by <hi>E:</hi> 3. and Knights of the <hi>Bath</hi> by <hi>H:</hi> 6.<note place="margin">Mils pag. <hi>24.</hi>
               </note> to take place of Knights Bachelors? and yet were they ſubſequent <hi>Dignities</hi> vnto them. And hath not the place beene ever given at the Prince his pleaſure, and ſometimes the Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cedencie before them of the ſame degree, though they were after them created. <hi>Vide Rot: Parl;</hi> 23.<note place="margin">Ch. a. <hi>23.</hi> H. <hi>6.</hi> memb. <hi>26.</hi> n. <hi>24. See</hi> Camden Brit. pag. <hi>570.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>H:</hi> 6. where King <hi>H:</hi> 6. granted to <hi>Henry Earle of Warwicke,</hi>
               <note place="margin">And it appeares in the <hi>Cha. ab anno</hi> 27. <hi>vſ<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan>
                  </hi> 37. <hi>H.</hi> 6. <hi>n.</hi> 24. <hi>&amp; Orig.</hi> 31. <hi>H.</hi> 6 <hi>Rot.</hi> 27. That af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terwards <hi>H.</hi> 6. created <hi>Edmond Hadham Earle of Richmond,</hi> and to take his place as the firſt Earle of England.</note> this Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eminence to be the firſt, and chiefe Earle of <hi>England,</hi> and to carry this Style, ſc<hi rend="sup">t</hi>. <hi>Henricus Praecomes totius Angliae, &amp; Comes Warwici,</hi> and after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards created him <hi>Duke of War<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wick,</hi> and by theſe expreſſe words of his Patent, granted that hee ſhould take his place in Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, and elſewhere,<note place="margin">Camden Brit. pag: <hi>570.</hi>
               </note> next vnto the <hi>Duke of Norfolke,</hi> and before
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:6468:5"/>
the <hi>Duke of Buckingham:</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Ch.</hi> 25. <hi>&amp;</hi> 26. <hi>H.</hi> 6 <hi>memb.</hi> 31.</note> 
               <hi>Vide</hi> 25. <hi>&amp;</hi> 26. <hi>H:</hi> 6. <hi>Humfridus Stafford Dux Buckingham, quod ſit primus Ducum in Anglia.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Billae ſignatae anno <hi>21.</hi> &amp; <hi>22.</hi> H. <hi>8.</hi>
               </note> See 21. <hi>&amp;</hi> 22. <hi>H:</hi> 8. <hi>a Grante to Anne Rochford of the Dignitie of Marchioneſſe of Pen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>broke, to take her place before all of her ranck, excepting the Kings Iſſue: Vide</hi> 18.<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pat.</hi> 18. <hi>H.</hi> 6. <hi>parte</hi> 2. <hi>memb.</hi> 20. <hi>&amp;</hi> 23. <hi>H.</hi> 6. This was the firſt honorary, and hereditary Viſcount after the Conqueſt.</note> 
               <hi>H:</hi> 6. <hi>Rex</hi> 12<hi rend="sup">0</hi> 
               <hi>die Februarij conceſsit Iohanni Domino de Beau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mont, nomen Vicecomitis de Beau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mont, cum</hi> 20. <hi>marcis percipiendis annuatim ſibi, &amp; haeredibus ſuis ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſculis; &amp; quod habeat locum ante, &amp; ſupra omnes Vicecomites fiendos, ſive creandos, &amp; haeredes, &amp; filios omnium Comitum, ac ſedem, &amp; hono<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> immediate, &amp; proxime Comitibus regni Angliae, in Parliame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tis: &amp;c. Vide a:</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>2.</hi> Parte Pat. an. <hi>1.</hi> E. <hi>4.</hi> memb. <hi>13.</hi>
               </note> 1. <hi>E:</hi> 4 <hi>Robertus Botill Prior Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpitalis ſancti Iohannis Ieruſalem. in Anglia,</hi>
               <note place="margin">See alſo <hi>Selden Hon. pag.</hi> 283.</note> 
               <hi>primus Baro Regni Angliae, &amp;c.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pat. anno <hi>5.</hi> H. <hi>3.</hi> memb. <hi>5.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Et vide a:</hi> 5. <hi>H:</hi> 3. <hi>Rex &amp;c. ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lutem: Obtentu dilecti Militis noſtri
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:6468:5"/>
Domini Rogeri de Leyburne, volen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes ipſum propter ipſius grata merita, &amp; accepta ſervitia culmini noſtro gratanter impenſa benigno favore proſequi, &amp; dilectione; vniverſitatem veſtram affectuoſe rogamus, quate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nus ipſum vbicun<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> locorum, de cae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tero tanquam noſtrum Militem ob no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtram reverentiam honore debito velitis proſequi, &amp; gratia ſpeciali, &amp;c.</hi> Hath not his Maieſtie the like po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wer? And wherein is this creation of <hi>Baronets</hi> more grievous, and hurtfull, then thoſe former here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditary <hi>Dignities</hi> were? Was there ever any exception taken to them? No not any. It is ſaid onely that King <hi>R:</hi> 2.<note place="margin">Camden Brit. pag. <hi>165.</hi> &amp;. <hi>217.</hi>
               </note> made <hi>Iohn of Beaufort ſonne to Iohn of Gaunt,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Selden Hon. pag. <hi>217.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>and Earle of Somerſet Marqueſſe of Dorſet;</hi> of which hee was afterwards depri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved by King <hi>H:</hi> 4. And when a Petition was in Parliament by the Commons for his reſtitution, hee
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:6468:6"/>
moſt humbly prayed the King, that in regard the name of Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queſſe was a ſtrange name in this Kingdome, that hee would not reſtore him to it, neyther would hee willingly accept thereof: which for your better ſatisfaction herein, there is here exemplified the Record it ſelfe, <hi>in haec verba,</hi> ſc<hi rend="sup">t</hi>. <hi>Rotulo Parliamenti,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Parl.</hi> 4. <hi>H.</hi> 4. <hi>memb.</hi> 18. <hi>Art.</hi> 18</note> 
               <hi>a:</hi> 4. <hi>H:</hi> 4. <hi>n:</hi> 18. <hi>Le lundy lo</hi> 6. <hi>jourde Novemb. les Commons viendrent devant le Roi, &amp; les Sn<hi rend="sup">rs.</hi> en Parlement, &amp; entre autres choſes, et matires illonques monſtrez, et parlez; Meſme les Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons humblament recomendantz les bone, et honorable port, et governance del Conte de Somerſet, prierent au Roi, que meſme le Conte, purroit eſtre reſtore a ſes noſme, et honour de Marquis, queux il avoit per devant, de quel prier, le Roi, et le Sn<hi rend="sup">rs.</hi> enun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tierent les dits Coe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s. Et le Roi lour deſoit quil voiloit eſtre aviſe, et ent
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:6468:6"/>
faire ceo que luy ſembleroit pur le mieux touchant cel matire, Et ſur ceo le dit Conte engenulant, mult hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blament pria au Roi, que comme le noſme de Marquis feuiſt eſtrange noſme en ceſt Roialme, quil ne luy voiloit aſcunement doner cel noſme de Marquis; quar jammais per con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gie du Roi il ne voiloit porter n'ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cepter ſur luy nul tiel noſme, en a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcun manner: mais nient meins le Conte molt cordialment remercia les Sn<hi rend="sup">rs.</hi> et les Coe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s de lour bone coers, et volente en celle partie.</hi> And herewithall whoſoever will ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve: firſt how the ſaid <hi>Iohn of Beaufort Earle of Somerſet</hi> obtai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned this <hi>Dignitie</hi> of <hi>Marques a:</hi> 21. <hi>R:</hi> 2. Secondly, that in Parliam<hi rend="sup">t</hi> 
               <hi>a:</hi>
               <note place="margin">Rot. Parl. anno <hi>21.</hi> R. <hi>2.</hi>
               </note> 1. <hi>H:</hi> 4. He was there diſhonored,<note place="margin">Rot. Parl. anno <hi>1.</hi> H. <hi>4.</hi>
               </note> &amp; deprived of this <hi>Dignity.</hi> Laſtly, the Kings anſwer to his ſaid Petiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on made by the interceſſion of the Commons in Parliament, <hi>a:</hi> 4. <hi>H:</hi>
               <note place="margin">Rot. Parl. a. <hi>4.</hi> H. <hi>4.</hi>
               </note> 4
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:6468:7"/>
               <hi>That hee would be adviſed, and doe that which ſhould ſeeme vnto him the beſt in that behalfe;</hi> hee may then plainly diſcerne, in what manner hee did refuſe it. Yet admit he did, what will they conclude of this, that becauſe one hath no ſtomack, therefore others muſt faſt alſo: I thinke few will like of this rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon. And though in diſtribution of <hi>Honors,</hi> his Maieſtie is not li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mited, or tyed to Precedent, but being the fountaine of <hi>Honor</hi> may create what <hi>Dignities</hi> he pleaſeth, and may as well conferre <hi>Honors</hi> vpon any man,<note place="margin">Davis Reports f. <hi>25.</hi>
               </note> as he may give value, or worth to any mettall to make it of eſteeme, and cur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent: Yet it is eaſie to prove (what opinions ſoever there are to the contrary) that the name of <hi>Baronet</hi> is no ſtrange name in this King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome.<note place="margin">Camden Brit. pag. <hi>171.</hi> Selden Hon. pag. <hi>354.</hi> &amp; <hi>355.</hi>
               </note> 
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>13</hi> E. <hi>3. and appeareth,</hi> clanſ. de anno <hi>15.</hi> E. <hi>4.</hi> memb. <hi>11.</hi> pro Willo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. Norreys Milite liberate.</note> 
               <hi>Vide temp. E.</hi> 3. <hi>Thomas de Bradeſton per Regem E:</hi> 3. 15. <hi>Octo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bris
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:6468:7"/>
anno regni ſui</hi> 13. <hi>factus Baro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nettus; cui, vt ipſe ſtatum Baronetti eo decentius manutenere queat, Rex dedit</hi> 500. <hi>marcas annuas habendas ſibi, &amp;c.</hi> See alſo the printed Stat: of 13. <hi>R:</hi> 2. <hi>ca:</hi> 1. <hi>&amp;</hi> 14. <hi>R:</hi> 2. <hi>ca:</hi> 11.<note place="margin">2. <hi>Stat.</hi> 13. <hi>R.</hi> 2. <hi>cap.</hi> 1. <hi>&amp;</hi> 14. <hi>R.</hi> 2. <hi>cap.</hi> 11.</note> for <hi>Baronets, &amp; vide anno</hi> 24. <hi>H:</hi> 6.<note place="margin">Originale de anno <hi>24.</hi> H. <hi>6.</hi> Rot. <hi>31.</hi> Aquiten.</note> 
               <hi>Rex</hi> 18. <hi>die Septembris conceſsit Rai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mundo de Pys Baronet Capitan: &amp; balliagium de Sauvetere, habend' pro termino vitae ſuae ad valorem</hi> 4. <hi>li. per annum.</hi> See alſo the booke caſe of 35. <hi>H:</hi> 6. for <hi>Baronet.</hi>
               <note place="margin">35. <hi>H.</hi> 6. <hi>f.</hi> 46.</note> It ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peares alſo by certaine Court-rols, and Evidences in <hi>E:</hi> 4. time,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Temp. E.</hi> 4. Theſe remaine in the hands of one M<hi rend="sup">r</hi>. <hi>Gittins</hi> of <hi>Burntwood</hi> in <hi>Eſſex.</hi>
               </note> that one Sir <hi>William Craiford of Mun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gham in Kent,</hi> had then, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in, the title, and addition of <hi>Baro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>net Vide</hi> 4. <hi>&amp;</hi> 5. <hi>H:</hi> 8.<note place="margin">Billae ſignatae annis <hi>4.</hi> &amp; <hi>5.</hi> H. <hi>8.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Rex Omni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bus ad quos, &amp;c. ſalutem.</hi>
               <note place="margin">See alſo <hi>Holinſhed Chron. pag. n.</hi> (his 3. volume for 322. 40. a. <hi>Baronets.</hi> 331. 30 b. <hi>Baronets.</hi> 359. 60. a. <hi>Baronets.</hi> 373. 60 a. <hi>Baronets.</hi> 384. 10. a. <hi>Baronets.</hi> 865. 10. b. <hi>Baronets.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Sciatis quod nos defidelitate, providentia, ſtrenui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tate, et induſtria, diligentia<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan>, et ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perientia, ac integritate chariſsimi Conſanguinei, et Conſiliarij noſtri
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:6468:8"/>
Georgij Comitis Salop: Seneſcalli Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpitij noſtri, ac Militis Ordinis noſtri Garterij plurimum confidentes: cun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dem locum tenentem noſtrum genera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lem, Ducemque primarium, &amp; guber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>natorem totius primae acici, et exer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>citus, ac Armatae noſtrae, favente al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſsimo, ad partes exter as profecturae, ac omnium, et ſingulorum Capitane<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>orum, vicecapitaneorum, et locate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nentium, Baronum, Baronettorum conſtituimus,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Billae ſignatae anno <hi>4.</hi> E. <hi>6.</hi> &amp; O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riginale de eodem anno, Rot. <hi>20.</hi> &amp; <hi>9.</hi> parte Paten. <hi>4.</hi> E. <hi>6.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>&amp;c. vide</hi> 4. <hi>E.</hi> 6. <hi>Rex &amp;c. Cum in conſideratione fidelis, et acceptabilis ſervitij nobis per dilectu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſervientem noſtrum Radul: Fane Militem in guerris noſtris, quam ali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter antehac facti, et impenſi, idem Radu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s ad Statum, Gradum, Hono<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rem, et Dignitatem Baronetti per nos erectus, ſuſcitatus, et creatus extite<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Billae ſignata anno <hi>1.</hi> Maria Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginae.</note> 
               <hi>&amp;c. Et vide</hi> 1. <hi>Maria; Williel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mus Howard Miles Dominus Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward de Effingham, magnus Admi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rallus Angliae, Wallia, Hiberniae,
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:6468:8"/>
Normanniae, Gaſconiae, et Aquitaniae fit locum-tenens generalis; Dux<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> primarius, et Gubernator totius Claſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſis armatae noſtrae regiae, in quibuſcun<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> partibus ſuper mare, ad tuitionem, et defenſionem Amicorum noſtrorum pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fecturae, ac omnium, et ſinguloru<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vium, Capitaneorum, et locum-tenen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tium, Baronum, Baronettorum, &amp;c.</hi> Yet notwithſtanding the teſtimo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny of theſe, and others, I will not affirme, that the diſtinct, and here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditary <hi>Dignity</hi> of <hi>Baronets</hi> was ever knowne vnto vs, before the Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of them by our preſent Sove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raigne:<note place="margin">See 2. Stat. 5. <hi>R.</hi> 2. <hi>ca.</hi> 4. in the Abridgements of Stat. for Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ronet, and in the Stat. at large Baneret, and yee ſhall alſo finde the ſame perſon in one and the ſelfe-ſame Record, ſomtimes written Baronet, and ſomtimes Baneret. For which ſee that of <hi>Bradeſton,</hi> 13. <hi>E.</hi> 3.</note> For I am not ignorant of the opinions of the learned con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning the former, that <hi>Baronu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lus, Baronettus, et Banerettus,</hi> were aunciently all one, and were pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſcuouſly vſed for <hi>Banerets.</hi> Tou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching this kinde of hereditary Knighthood,<note place="margin">See <hi>Mils pag.</hi> 24. that there are hereditary Knights at this day in <hi>Italy.</hi>
               </note> which (ſay they) was never before heard of, ſee the
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:6468:9"/>
Patents in 13.<note place="margin">
                  <p>
                     <hi>Rot. Vaſcon</hi> 13. <hi>E.</hi> 3. <hi>memb</hi> 13. For this alſo you haue an Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thor entituled, <hi>The Treaſury of Times, pag.</hi> 527. herewith con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curring.</p>
                  <p>And it is further proved <hi>ex clauſ.</hi> 7. <hi>R.</hi> 2. <hi>memb.</hi> 32. <hi>in dorſo.</hi>
                  </p>
               </note> 
               <hi>E:</hi> 3. vnto <hi>William de la Pole,</hi> and the like vnto <hi>Bradeſton;</hi> which ſheweth that <hi>Banerets</hi> were then hereditary, &amp; that for main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenance of their <hi>Dignity,</hi> lands were given vnto them and their heyres. And our auncient feoda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry Knights,<note place="margin">
                  <p>Math. Paris pag. <hi>1249. Stat. 1.</hi> E. <hi>2. 7.</hi> H. <hi>6.</hi> f. <hi>14. 15. See</hi> Camdens Brit. pag. <hi>174.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>That they fined for not being knighted. See alſo</hi> Selden Hon. pag. <hi>319. 320.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Vide Dorſo clauſarum de anno <hi>3.</hi> H. <hi>3.</hi> memb. <hi>24.</hi> Quiſquis Laicus plenae aetatis, qui feodu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> vnius Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litis tenet, &amp; Miles non eſt, arma capiat, &amp; ſe Militem fieri faciat, ſicut feodum vel feoda ſua diligit.</p>
               </note> here in <hi>England,</hi> were in a manner hereditary: For, if a Knights fee which was 20. li. land <hi>per annu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>,</hi> had deſcended vnto one, he was compellable to take, and it ſeemeth, of right might have de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded a Knighthood, and alſo the armes, &amp; equipage of Knight<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hood, which belonged to a Knights Fee; That is to ſay, <hi>His Horſe,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Selden Hon. pag <hi>321. 322.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Speare, Sword, and Target</hi> was to deſcend vnto the heire, and not to goe to the executors, as it is of other perſonall things. For this reade likewiſe <hi>Roger Hoveden.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Roger Hoveden pag <hi>611. 614.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>The Conſtitutions vnder King H:</hi> 2. ſc<hi rend="sup">t</hi>. <hi>Quicun<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> habet Feodu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> vnius Militis,
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:6468:9"/>
habeat loricam, et Caſsidem,</hi>
               <note place="margin">See <hi>Ranulphus f.</hi> 61. and in the end of the old <hi>Mag. Char. f.</hi> 168. and <hi>Selden Hon. pag.</hi> 278. That of theſe Knights fees, there were aunciently in this King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome many thouſands, and of Baronies 250. at one time.</note> 
               <hi>&amp; cly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peum, &amp; lanceam, &amp; omnis Miles habeat tot loricas, caſsides, clypeos, &amp; lanceas quot habuerit feoda Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litum in Dominio ſuo, &amp; ſi quis haec habens arma obierit, arma ſua rema<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neant haeredi ſuo, &amp; ſi haeres de tali aetate non ſit, quod armis vti poſsit, ſi opus fuerit, ille eum qui habebit in cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtodia, habeat ſimiliter cuſtodiam ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>morum, &amp; inveniat hominem, qui armis vti poſsit in ſervitio Domini Regis, ſi opus fuerit, donec haeres de tali aetate ſit,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Vide Fleta li. <hi>9.</hi> ca. <hi>9.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>quod arma portare poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſit, tunc ea habeat.</hi> By which alſo, as by this that followeth out of <hi>Bracton,</hi> and others, it appeareth,<note place="margin">Bracton fol. <hi>5.</hi>
               </note> that from our auncient Nobilitie aroſe the principall ſtrength, and faſegard of this Land,<note place="margin">
                  <p>Vide Rot. Parl. anno <hi>21.</hi> R. <hi>2.</hi> viz. Pur ceo que le greinder ſupporta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion de cheſcun Realme conſiſte des dignes perſon's de ſtate, &amp; de ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nor que purront enforcer, &amp; forti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fier le Scepter du Roi, &amp;c.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>See alſo the Preambles of Let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters Patents for creation of</hi> Dig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nities <hi>accord.</hi>
                  </p>
               </note> (who wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth thus of thoſe that were in his time,) <hi>Comites, quia à Comitatu, ſive ſocietate nomen ſumpſerunt, qui etiam dici poſſunt Conſules a conſulendo,
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:6468:10"/>
Reges enim tales ſibi aſſociant, ad conſulendum,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Vide Hotoman, li. <hi>1.</hi> Feud. Tit. <hi>1. §. 1.</hi> &amp; tit. <hi>7.</hi> Alij ſunt Capitanei Regni, quo verbo Duces, Comites, Marchiones, intelliguntur.</note> 
               <hi>&amp; regendum populum Dei, ordinantes eos in magno hono<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re, poteſtate, &amp; nomine, quando accingunt eos gladijs: Gladius au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tem ſignificat defenſionem Regni, &amp; Patriae: Sunt &amp; alij Potentes ſub Rege,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <p>Vide Bracton, li. <hi>2.</hi> ca. <hi>34.</hi> f. <hi>76.</hi> Niſi capitale Meſuagium illud ſit caput Baroniae propter ius Gladij, &amp;c.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>See</hi> Camden Brit. pag. <hi>175. Knight aunciently the name of charge, and function.</hi>
                  </p>
               </note> 
               <hi>qui dicuntur Barones, hoc eſt Robur belli: Sunt &amp; ſub Rege Milites,</hi> ſc<hi rend="sup">t</hi>. <hi>ad Militiam exercen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dam electi, vt cum Rege, &amp; ſupra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dictis militent, &amp; defendant Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>triam, &amp; Populum Dei, &amp;c.</hi> And as you haue heard how by theſe Dignities, and Perſons of Honor, this Kingdome was aunciently fortified, and defended, ſo ſhall you likewiſe finde, that by this encreaſe of <hi>Dignitie,</hi> there will be an increaſe of ſtrength to the Common-wealth; and that theſe will be eminent, whenas others peradventure of greater abilitie,<note place="margin">Vide Iohan. Baſanum, li. <hi>2.</hi> pag. <hi>125.</hi> Sicut Coelum ſtellis, ſic terra Nobilibus, &amp; heroicis perſonis in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſignitur.</note> will neyther deſire, nor deſerve
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:6468:10"/>
               <hi>Honor,</hi> but rather ſeeke obſcuri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie to ſhunne the charges of the Common-weale; then be diſco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vered, vpon the Act of 33.<note place="margin">By this Act of 33. <hi>H.</hi> 8. ca. 5. Certaine perſons nobled are to finde a horſe for ſervice, &amp; ſuch whoſe wives ſhall weare, any ſilke, or Velvet, gold, pearle, or pretious ſtone.</note> of King <hi>H:</hi> 8. to finde Armes for defence of their Countrie, though it were in time of greateſt neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitie. And that the publique good is advanced by this addition of <hi>Honor,</hi> heare alſo the opinion of a principall Secretary to King <hi>E:</hi> 6. who holds,<note place="margin">Smiths Common-wealth of Engl. pag. <hi>29.</hi>
               </note> that the more <hi>Dignities</hi> there are, the better it is for the Common-wealth: For ſaith hee, the Gentleman is more charged then the Yeoman, which hee beareth the gladlier, and dare not gaineſay it, for to ſave, and keepe his honor, and reputa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and in any Shew, or Mu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter, or other particular Charge of the place wherein hee is reſident, as for the poore, or otherwiſe, hee opens his purſe
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:6468:11"/>
wider, and augments his portion aboue others, or elſe he doth di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miniſh his reputation. For this you may reade him at large. To returne to the matter, and to an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer him who holds that this <hi>Dig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity</hi> of <hi>Baronets</hi> is againſt the Law, becauſe no hereditary <hi>Dignity</hi> (as hee would haue it) can be entailed within the Statute of <hi>Weſtm<hi rend="sup">r</hi>.</hi> 2.<note place="margin">Stat. <hi>Weſtm<hi rend="sup">r</hi>.</hi> 2 <hi>ca.</hi> 1.</note> but it muſt haue relation to a Realtie, and haue lands to goe therewith: I confeſſe his opinion may well agree with the phraſe in our writs; <hi>Quod injuſtè,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Regiſter of Writs, <hi>f.</hi> 196.</note> 
               <hi>et ſine judicio cepit, &amp;c.</hi> And according to this vaine runs his tongue,<note place="margin">F. na. br. f. <hi>177.</hi>
               </note> but not with the Law: For vnleſſe it were by him,<note place="margin">See <hi>Co. li.</hi> 7. <hi>f.</hi> 33.</note> it was never ſo adjudged: And hee may learne thus much, that conſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions of <hi>Dignities</hi> are not alwaies taken according to the ſtrict rules of the Common-Law: Nor if you are to try the right of a <hi>Dignity,</hi>
               <pb n="19" facs="tcp:6468:11"/>
ſhall it be tryed by Iury;<note place="margin">Co. li <hi>11.</hi> f. <hi>1.</hi> Mils pag. <hi>71.</hi>
               </note> neyther doe the Maximes,<note place="margin">Vide Rot. Parl. apud Weſtm<hi rend="sup">r</hi>. anno <hi>27.</hi> H. <hi>6.</hi> memb. <hi>4.</hi> Art. <hi>18.</hi>
               </note> or grounds in Law, hold in matter of <hi>Honor,</hi> for there is no copercenary of a <hi>Dig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity;</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Bracton li.</hi> 2. <hi>cap.</hi> 34. <hi>f.</hi> 76. <hi>Mils pag.</hi> 27. See alſo the Cuſtomes of <hi>Nor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandy, f.</hi> 120. <hi>Mils pag.</hi> 76.</note> nor haue you a Tenant by the courteſie of a <hi>Dignity:</hi> neyther is there <hi>Poſſeſsio fratris</hi> of a <hi>Dignity:</hi>
               <note place="margin">Co. li. <hi>3.</hi> f. <hi>42.</hi>
               </note> No more can a <hi>Dignity</hi> be tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferred, though it be given to a man and to his heyres. And whereas it is obiected, that <hi>Baronets</hi> being an hereditary <hi>Dignity,</hi> if they fall into poverty, they and their heires ſhall notwithſtanding take the place of Knights. I anſwer, that this is a chance incident vnto all <hi>Dignities,</hi> and to Knighthood al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo: yet that there is a remedy for this, and the like grievance, they may vnderſtand, that if the poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſſions of any perſons nobled are ſo decayed,<note place="margin">Smiths Common-wealth of En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gland, pag. <hi>21. 22.</hi> Mils pag. <hi>29.</hi>
               </note> that they haue not wherewith to ſupport their <hi>Dig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity,</hi> there is a meanes to deprive
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:6468:12"/>
them of it.<note place="margin">Rot. Parl. anno <hi>17.</hi> E. <hi>4.</hi>
               </note> See how in 17. <hi>E:</hi> 4. <hi>Iohn Marques Montague,</hi> and <hi>George Duke of Bedford,</hi> were by Act of Parliament degraded of all hono<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable Titles in theſe words, ſc<hi rend="sup">t</hi>. Whereas afore this time, the King our Soveraigne Lord, for the great love, and zeale he bare to <hi>Iohn Ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vill,</hi> late named <hi>Marques Montague,</hi> and other conſiderations him mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving, did erect and make <hi>George Nevill</hi> the eldeſt ſonne of the ſaid <hi>Marques,</hi> to be <hi>Duke</hi> of <hi>Bedford:</hi> And at that time, for the great love, that his ſaid <hi>Highnes</hi> bare to the ſaid <hi>Iohn Nevill,</hi> purpoſed, and intended to haue given to the ſaid <hi>George</hi> for ſuſtentation of the ſame <hi>Dignity</hi> ſufficient livelihood: and for the great offences, vnkindnes, and misbehavings that the ſaid <hi>Iohn Nevill</hi> hath done, and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted to his ſaid <hi>Highnes</hi> (as is o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>penly knowne) hee hath no cauſe
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:6468:12"/>
to depart any livelihood vnto the ſaid <hi>George:</hi> And foraſmuch as it is openly knowne, that the ſaid <hi>George</hi> hath not, nor by inheri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance may have any Livelihood to ſupport the ſaid <hi>Name, Eſtate,</hi> and <hi>Dignity,</hi> or any name of <hi>E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtate.</hi> And oftentimes it is ſeene, that when any Lord is called to high eſtate, and hath not liveli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hood conveniently to ſupport the ſaid <hi>Dignitie,</hi> it induceth great povertie, and indigence, and cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth oftentimes great extortion, embracery, and maintenance to be had, to the great trouble of all ſuch Countries, where ſuch Eſtate ſhall happen to inhabit: Where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the King by the advice, and conſent of his Lords, ſpirituall, &amp; temporall, and of the Commons of this preſent Parliament aſſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled, and by the auctoritie of the ſame, hath ordained, eſtabliſhed,
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:6468:13"/>
and enacted, that from hence<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forth the ſaid erection, and ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king of <hi>Duke,</hi> and all the names of <hi>Dignity</hi> given to the ſaid <hi>George,</hi> or to the ſaid <hi>Iohn Nevill</hi> his fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, be from henceforth void, and of none effect: And that the ſaid <hi>George,</hi> and his heires, from henceforth be no <hi>Dukes,</hi> nor <hi>Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queſſes, Earles,</hi> nor <hi>Barons,</hi> for no erection, or creation before made: But that the name of <hi>Duke,</hi> and <hi>Marques, Earle,</hi> and <hi>Baron,</hi> in him, and his heires, ceaſe, and be void, and of none effect (the ſaid Erecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, or Creation notwithſtanding. Yee ſhall alſo reade in <hi>Nevils</hi> Caſe reported of by Sir <hi>Edw:</hi>
               <note place="margin">Co. li. <hi>7.</hi> f. <hi>33.</hi> &amp; <hi>34.</hi> Quinetiam ſi poſteaquam electus eſſet Senator Cenſum labefactaſſet, Ordinem amittebat. Sigonius de antiquo iure Civiu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Rom. li. <hi>2.</hi> ca. <hi>2.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Coke,</hi> that, As in auncient times the Senators of <hi>Rome</hi> were elected <hi>à Cenſu,</hi> of their Revenues: ſo, in former times in conferring of <hi>Nobilitie</hi> here with vs; there was reſpect had vnto their Revenues, by
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:6468:13"/>
which their <hi>Dignitie</hi> and <hi>Nobilitie</hi> might be ſupported, and maintai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned; through the want whereof great miſchiefe may enſue:<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Britton f.</hi> 68. 29, <hi>E.</hi> 3. <hi>f.</hi> 42. 11. <hi>H.</hi> 4. <hi>f.</hi> 15. 1. <hi>H.</hi> 5. <hi>f.</hi> 14. 14. <hi>H.</hi> 6: <hi>f.</hi> 2. <hi>Co. li.</hi> 6. <hi>f.</hi> 52.</note> For no <hi>Capias</hi> lyeth againſt a Lord of the Parliament,<note place="margin">Id ſolum privilegium habent No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>biles a regibus in gratificationem obſequiûm Reipublicae. Molin. Tract. <hi>2.</hi> pag. <hi>1456.</hi>
               </note> in that the Law pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſumes he hath ſufficient freehold <hi>ad ſuſtinendum nomen, &amp; onus,</hi> and wherewith to ſatisfie eyther debt, or treſpaſſe; the which wanting, all remedy in ſuch caſe faileth: Therefore Antiquitie hath ſet downe a Competencie of liveli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hood for theſe degrees following,<note place="margin">Co. li. <hi>9.</hi> f. <hi>124.</hi>
               </note> ſc<hi rend="sup">t</hi>. 12. Plough-lands for a Knights fee, as ſufficient to maintaine the degree of Knighthood: 13.<note place="margin">Co. li. <hi>7.</hi> f. <hi>33.</hi> &amp; <hi>34.</hi>
               </note> Knights fees to be a convenient living for a <hi>Baron:</hi> 20. for an <hi>Earle:</hi> 26. for a <hi>Marques:</hi> 40. for a <hi>Duke.</hi> Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to which, his Maieſtie hath likewiſe beene pleaſed to ſet downe the revenue of a <hi>Baronet,</hi>
               <note place="margin">The Booke publiſhed by his Maieſtie touching Baronets, <hi>pag.</hi> 17. printed 1611.</note> to be 1000. li. land <hi>per annum de
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:6468:14"/>
claro,</hi> of Inheritance, whereof two parts at the leaſt to be in poſſeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, and the third in reverſion. And though true it is, that, <hi>Vtilior eſt ſapientia cum divitijs conjuncta:</hi>
               <note place="margin">Lamb. Peramb. pag. <hi>368.</hi>
               </note> Yet it is not hereby intended,<note place="margin">Qui vtiliter, &amp; decenter Magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrat fungi debent, ſint divites bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nis animi, doctrinae, iuſtitiae, ſapi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>entiae, pietatis auro abundent. Plato li. <hi>7.</hi> de Repub.</note> that vertue is meaſured by the acre, or that it conſiſts in riches: For ſtrength is not alwayes found by greatnes,<note place="margin">Fulbeck li. vlt. ca. <hi>9.</hi> f. <hi>67.</hi>
               </note> nor in multitude, no more is inward ability by outward wealth:<note place="margin">See Stat. 18. <hi>H.</hi> 6. <hi>ca.</hi> 11. 9. <hi>E.</hi> 2. 4. <hi>E.</hi> 3. 9. 5. <hi>E.</hi> 3. 4. 14. <hi>E.</hi> 3. 8. 1. <hi>H.</hi> 8. 8. 3. <hi>H.</hi> 8. 2. 35. <hi>H.</hi> 8. 6. 2. <hi>E.</hi> 6. 32. &amp; Stat. 27. <hi>Eliz. cap.</hi> 6.</note> Nor were thoſe Lawes which require freehold in Iuſtices, Shierieves, Coroners, Eſcheators, Iurors,<note place="margin">Regiſter of Writs, <hi>f.</hi> 178. 12. <hi>H.</hi> 7. <hi>f.</hi> 4.</note> and Bailiffes of Liberties, made out of any other reſpects, then meerly to the end, that if theſe tranſgreſſe in their office, or duty, they ſhould render ſatisfa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction for it, as well by their eſtates, as otherwiſe. To conclude, ſeeing it is his <hi>Highnes</hi> pleaſure to create this <hi>Dignity,</hi> and in that, it is law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully granted, and is no way more
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:6468:14"/>
preiudicious in the continuance, then any other former hereditary <hi>Dignity</hi> is, or hath beene: And it ſo being, that his Maieſtie, who is the chiefe <hi>Iudge</hi> of vertue, and me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit, is pleaſed to eſteeme them worthy of this <hi>Dignity,</hi> it is not for you nor any then to diſpute it. See Sir <hi>Drue Duries</hi> Caſe,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Co. li.</hi> 6. <hi>f.</hi> 73. 74.</note> that if the King knighteth one within age: who is vnable to doe Knights ſervice, <hi>Tout's ſont conclude à dira le contrarie de ceo, pur ceo, quant le Roi, que eſt le ſovereigne, &amp; ſupreme Iudge de Chivalrie, ad dubbe luy Chi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>valer; il per ceo ad adiudge luy able.</hi> See likewiſe the auncient Lawes of this Land, both before,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>See</hi> Ranulphus f. <hi>61.</hi> Saxon <hi>in his deſcription of En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gland,</hi> cap. <hi>71.</hi> Britton f. <hi>49. b.</hi> Bal. l. Obſer. Petrus Geral. in ſuis Singular. <hi>33.</hi>
               </note> and ſince the Conqueſt; and alſo the Civill-Law, againſt traducing of <hi>Honor,</hi> or <hi>Worſhip.</hi> And ſee 2,<note place="margin">2. Pet. 2.10. in the laſt Tranſla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion. Iude 8.</note> of <hi>Peter</hi> 2.10. <hi>Preſumptuous are they, ſelfwilled, they are not afraid to ſpeake evill of Dignities.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Camdens Remaines pag. <hi>138.</hi>
               </note> See <hi>Camdens Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mains,</hi>
               <pb n="26" facs="tcp:6468:15"/>
or in the <hi>Code</hi> of <hi>Theodoſius;</hi>
               <note place="margin">Codicis Theodos. li. <hi>6.</hi> Tit. <hi>5.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Tit. Vt Dignitatum ordo ſervetur: Si quis indebitum ſibi locum vſurpa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verit, nulla <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e ignoratione defendat, ſit<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> plane ſacrilegij reus.</hi>
            </p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:6468:15"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
